I want to talk about the transformed media landscape,
أريد ان أتحدث إليكم عن أفاق الإعلام المتغير
and what it means for anybody who has a message that they want to get out
وماذا تعني لكل من لديه رسالة يود ان تخرج
to anywhere in the world.
لأي مكان في العالم
And I want to illustrate that by telling a couple of stories
وأريد أستعرض ذلك بإخباركم قصتين
about that transformation.
عن ذلك التغيير
I'll start here. Last November there was a presidential election.
وسأبدأ هنا ، في نوفمبر الماضي كان هناك إنتخابات رئاسية
You probably read something about it in the papers.
انتم قد تقرأؤن شيئاً في الصحف
And there was some concern that in some parts of the country
وكان هناك بعض القلق انه بعض أطراف البلاد
there might be voter suppression.
أند قد يكون هناك تأثيرحزبي على الأصوات
And so a plan came up to video the vote.
وهنا أتت الخطة لتصوير الصوت الداعم
And the idea was that individual citizens
والفكرة كانت أن يقوم كل فرد مواطن
with phones capable of taking photos or making video
معه جوال قادر على إلتقاط الصور أو الفيديو
would document their polling places,
سيوثقون أماكن تصويتهم
on the lookout for any kind of voter suppression techniques,
للتمحيص حال وجود أي طرق للتأثير الحكومي
and would upload this to a central place.
وسيرفعون هذه التوثيقات لمكان مركزي
And that this would operate as a kind of citizen observation --
وهذا سيتصرف كنوع من الملاحظة الإجتماعية
that citizens would not be there just to cast individual votes,
بأن المواطنين لن يكونوا هناك فقط لتأدية صوت فردي
but also to help ensure the sanctity of the vote overall.
ولكن كذلك تساعد على تأكيد شفافية الإنتخابات بشكل عام
So this is a pattern that assumes we're all in this together.
وهذا نموذج نفترض فيه أننا في هذا سوياً
What matters here
ليست عاصمة تقنياً
isn't technical capital,
بل عاصمة إجتماعية
it's social capital.
هذه الأدوات لاتخلب إهتمام الجماهير
These tools don't get socially interesting
حتى تكون تقنياً مضجرة
until they get technologically boring.
أنه ليس عندما تظهر الأدوات اللماعه
It isn't when the shiny new tools show up
يبدأ أستخداماتها بإختراق المجتمع
that their uses start permeating society.
إنها عندما يتمكن الكل من الأستفادة القصوى منها
It's when everybody is able to take them for granted.
لأنه الآن هذا الإعلام يزداد إجتماعيتاً
Because now that media is increasingly social,
الإبتكار قد يحدث في أي مكان
innovation can happen anywhere
وبعض الناس يستعبطون على الأفكار وكلنا في هذا
that people can take for granted the idea that we're all in this together.
إذا نحن نبدأ برؤية أفق إعلامي
And so we're starting to see a media landscape
الذي فيه الإبتكار يحدث في كل مكان
in which innovation is happening everywhere,
وينتقل من مكان لأخر
and moving from one spot to another.
وهذا التغيير العظيم
That is a huge transformation.
وليس أن نضع نقطة نظام عليها ، في اللحظة التي نعيشها
Not to put too fine a point on it, the moment we're living through --
اللحظة التي يعيشها الجيل التاريخي
the moment our historical generation is living through --
هو أكبر زيادة في القدرة على التعبير
is the largest increase in expressive capability
في تاريخ البشرية
in human history.
الآن هذا هو عبارة كبيرة ، سأحاول هنا أن أدعمها بالأدلة
Now that's a big claim. I'm going to try to back it up.
هنالك فقط أربعه فترات في الخمسمائة سنة الماضية
There are only four periods in the last 500 years
التي تغير فيها وسائل الإعلام بشكل ثوري
where media has changed enough to qualify for the label "revolution."
أولها وأشهرها هو طباعه الصحف
The first one is the famous one, the printing press:
الأنواع المتنقلة ، والأحبار الزيتية ، ذلك التعقيد من الإبتكار
movable type, oil-based inks, that whole complex of innovations
الذي جعل الطباعة ممكنه
that made printing possible
وقد قلبت أوروبا رأس على عقب بداية من القرن الرابع عشر
and turned Europe upside-down, starting in the middle of the 1400s.
ثم منذ مئتي سنة مضت
Then, a couple of hundred years ago,
كان هناك أبتكار في التواصل من جهتين
there was innovation in two-way communication,
الإعلام المحادثي ، أولا التلقراف ، ثم الهاتف
conversational media: first the telegraph, then the telephone.
وببطء ، حوارات برسائل نصية
Slow, text-based conversations,
ثم محاثات صوتية آنية
then real-time voice based conversations.
ثم منذ 150 عام مضت
Then, about 150 years ago,
كان هناك ثورة في الإعلام المسجل أكثر من المطبوع
there was a revolution in recorded media other than print:
أولاً الصور، ثم الصوت المسجل،
first photos, then recorded sound,
ثم الأفلام، وكلها قد تم ترميزها إلى أشياء مدركة بالحواس
then movies, all encoded onto physical objects.
وأخيراً منذ 100 سنة مضت ، تقدم الأطياف الكهرومغناطيسية
And finally, about 100 years ago, the harnessing of electromagnetic spectrum
لترسل صوتاً وصوراً عبر الهواء ، راديو وتلفزيون
to send sound and images through the air -- radio and television.
هذا هو أفق الإعلام كما نعرفه في القرن العشرين
This is the media landscape as we knew it in the 20th century.
هذا الذي بعضنا في عمر معين
This is what those of us of a certain age
كبروا معه ، وتعودوا عليه
grew up with, and are used to.
ولكن هناك عدم توافق عجيب هنا
But there is a curious asymmetry here.
الإعلام الجيد في إقامة حوارات
The media that is good at creating conversations
ليس جيداً في إقامة مجموعات
is no good at creating groups.
وهذا جيد في إنشاء المجموعات
And the media that's good at creating groups
وليس جيد في بناء الحوارات
is no good at creating conversations.
إذا كنتم تريد إقامة حوار
If you want to have a conversation
في هذا العالم ، يجب أن يكون مع شخص أخر
in this world, you have it with one other person.
إذا كنت تريد أن توجه كلامك لمجموعه ، أنت تصلك نفس الرسالة
If you want to address a group, you get the same message
وأنت تعطيها لكل من في المجموعه
and you give it to everybody in the group,
سواء كنت تعمل ذلك ببرج بث أو مطبعه
whether you're doing that with a broadcasting tower or a printing press.
هذا كان أفق الإعلام
That was the media landscape
كما تلقيناه في القرن العشرين
as we had it in the twentieth century.
وهذا ما تغير
And this is what changed.
هذا الشي الذي يظهر كطاووس اصطدم بشاشة عريضة
This thing that looks like a peacock hit a windscreen
هو خريطة بيل شيس ويك للأنترنت
is Bill Cheswick's map of the Internet.
هو يراقب أطراف الشكبات الفردية
He traces the edges of the individual networks
ثم يمزهم بألوان
and then color codes them.
الأنترنت هي الوسيلة الأولي في التاريخ
The Internet is the first medium in history
التي تدعم المجموعات ببساطة
that has native support for groups
والحورات في نفس الوقت
and conversation at the same time.
بينما الهاتف أعطانا الحوار من فرد لفرد
Whereas the phone gave us the one-to-one pattern,
والتلفاز والمذياع والكتب
and television, radio, magazines, books,
أعطتنا نموذج الإتصال من طرف واحد للكل
gave us the one-to-many pattern,
الأنترنت أعطتنا نموذج التصال بين الكل والكل
the Internet gives us the many-to-many pattern.
لأول مرة
For the first time,
الإعلام وسيلة فطرية جيدة لدعم مثل هذه الحوارات
media is natively good at supporting these kinds of conversations.
هذا واحد من التغييرات العظيمة
That's one of the big changes.
التغير الكبير الثاني
The second big change
أن كل وسائل الإعلام يتم رقمنتها
is that, as all media gets digitized,
والأنترنت كذلك أصبحت وسيلة لحمل
the Internet also becomes the mode of carriage
بقية الوسائل
for all other media,
بمعني أن المحادثات الهاتفية تنقل عبر الأنترنت
meaning that phone calls migrate to the Internet,
المجلات تنقل عبر الأنترنت ، الأفلام كذلك
magazines migrate to the Internet, movies migrate to the Internet.
وهذا يعني أن كل وسيلة إعلامية
And that means that every medium
هي بجانب باب الوسيلة الإعلامية الأخرى
is right next door to every other medium.
ولكن بطريقة أخرى
Put another way,
الإعلام يتزايد كونه مصدراً للمعلومات
media is increasingly less just a source of information,
وهو يزيد من سبل التنسيق
and it is increasingly more a site of coordination,
لأنه المجموعات التي ترى أو تسمع أو تتابع أو تنصت لشي
because groups that see or hear or watch or listen to something
تستطيع الآن أن تجتمع وتتحادث مع بعضها البعض كذلك
can now gather around and talk to each other as well.
والتغيير الكبير الثالث
And the third big change
هو أن أعضاء من الحضور الأسبقين ، مثلما يسميهم دان قيلمور
is that members of the former audience, as Dan Gilmore calls them,
يستطيعون الآن الأنتاج وليس فقط الأستهلاك
can now also be producers and not consumers.
وفي كل مرة مستهلك جديد
Every time a new consumer
ينظم لأفق هذا الإعلام
joins this media landscape
منتج جديد ينظم كذلك
a new producer joins as well,
لأنه نفس الأدوات
because the same equipment --
الهواتف ، الحواسب ،
phones, computers --
تجعلكم تستهلكون وتنتجون
let you consume and produce.
كما لو أنكم أشتريتم كتاباً ، قد رمي للمطبعة ببلاش
It's as if, when you bought a book, they threw in the printing press for free;
وكأن لديك هاتف يتحول لمذياع
it's like you had a phone that could turn into a radio
إذا ضغطت الإزرار المناسب
if you pressed the right buttons.
هذا تغيير عظيم
That is a huge change
في أفق الإعلام الذي تعودنا عليه
in the media landscape we're used to.
وهو ليس فقط أما أنترنت أو لا أنترنت
And it's not just Internet or no Internet.
فنحن لدينا الأنترنت بشكلها العمومي
We've had the Internet in its public form
لقرابة 20 سنة الآن
for almost 20 years now,
وهي مازالت تتغير
and it's still changing
كلما يضل الإعلام إجتماعياً أكثر
as the media becomes more social.
هو مازال نموذج للتغيير
It's still changing patterns
حتى بين المجموعات التي تعرف كيفية التعامل مع الانترنت جيداً
even among groups who know how to deal with the Internet well.
القصة الثانية ،
Second story.
مايو الماضي ، الصين في محافظة سيشون
Last May, China in the Sichuan province
حصل زلزال عظيم بقوة 7.9 درجات
had a terrible earthquake, 7.9 magnitude,
دمار شامل في مناطق واسعه ، كما رصدها ريختر
massive destruction in a wide area, as the Richter Scale has it.
وقد رصدت الهزة الأرضية بأنها حدثت
And the earthquake was reported as it was happening.
الناس كانوا يتراسلوعبر هواتفهم ، كان يصورون المباني
People were texting from their phones. They were taking photos of buildings.
وكانوا يصورون أفلام للمباني تهتز
They were taking videos of buildings shaking.
وقد رفعوها لـ QQ أكبر موفر أنترنت في الصين
They were uploading it to QQ, China's largest Internet service.
وقد كانوا يتواترونها
They were Twittering it.
وعندما كانت الهزة قائمة
And so as the quake was happening
كانت الأخبار تبث
the news was reported.
وبسبب التواصل الأجتماعي
And because of the social connections,
الطلبة الصينين القادمين من مكان أخر ، أو ذاهبين للمدرسة
Chinese students coming elsewhere, and going to school,
أو الشركات التي لديها مكاتب تفتح في الصين
or businesses in the rest of the world opening offices in China --
كان هناك ناس يسمعون من جميع أنحاء العالم ، ينصتون لهذه لأخبار
there were people listening all over the world, hearing this news.
البي بي سي أخذت أول موجة من الزلزال عبر تويتر
The BBC got their first wind of the Chinese quake from Twitter.
تويتر أعلن وجود الزلزال
Twitter announced the existence of the quake
بضع دقائق قبل المرصد الجيولوجي الأمريكي
several minutes before the US Geological Survey
هل رفع شيئاً للأنترنت لشخص ما ليقرأه
had anything up online for anybody to read.
أخر مرة حصل زلزال في الصين بهذه القوة
The last time China had a quake of that magnitude
لقد أخذ منهم ثلاث أشهر ليعترفوا بأنها قد حصلت
it took them three months to admit that it had happened.
(ضحك) :)
(Laughter)
الآن هم قد يكونوا فضلوا عمل ذلك هنا
Now they might have liked to have done that here,
على أن يروا هذه الصور ترفع للنت
rather than seeing these pictures go up online.
ولكنهم لم يعطوا هذا الخيار
But they weren't given that choice,
لأنهم مواطنيهم غلبوهم كلياً
because their own citizens beat them to the punch.
حتى الحكومة عرفت عن الهزة الأرضية عبر مواطنيهم
Even the government learned of the earthquake from their own citizens,
فضلا عن وكالة أخبار شانهان
rather than from the Xinhua News Agency.
وهذه الأشياء تنتشر كالنار في الهشيم
And this stuff rippled like wildfire.
لفترة هنا
For a while there
أعلى 10 روابط تم ضربها في تويتر
the top 10 most clicked links on Twitter,
خدمة التراسل النصي العالمية
the global short messaging service --
9 من 10 كانت عن الهزة الأرضية
nine of the top 10 links were about the quake.
الناس يتشاركون المعلومات
People collating information,
مؤشرين على أناس أنهم مصدر الأخبار
pointing people to news sources,
تأشير الناس للمرصد الجيولوجي الأمريكي
pointing people to the US geological survey.
العاشر كان قطة على سير الجري
The 10th one was kittens on a treadmill, but that's the Internet for you.
(ضحك) :)
(Laughter)
ولكن 9 من ال 10 في تلك الساعات
But nine of the 10 in those first hours.
وفي خلال نصف يوم مواقع التبرعات قد رفعت
And within half a day donation sites were up,
والتبرعات كانت ترد من كل مكان حول العالم
and donations were pouring in from all around the world.
هذا كان غير معقول ، رد عالمي منظم
This was an incredible, coordinated global response.
والصينين ، في أحدى فترات أنفتاح إعلامهم
And the Chinese then, in one of their periods of media openness,
قرروا أن يدعوها تمر هذه المرة
decided that they were going to let it go,
وبأنهم سيدعون هذا التقرير المجتمعي أن يطير
that they were going to let this citizen reporting fly.
ثم حدث هذا
And then this happened.
بدأ الناس بأكتشاف ، في محافظة سيشوان
People began to figure out, in the Sichuan Provence,
بأن السبب في أن مباني المدارس قد تهدمت
that the reason so many school buildings had collapsed --
لأنه بكل اسى حصلت الهزة الأرضية في يوم مدرسي
because tragically the earthquake happened during a school day --
وسبب سقوط العديد من المباني المدرسية
the reason so many school buildings collapsed
هو الفساد الإداري الحمي الذي أخذ رشاوى
is that corrupt officials had taken bribes
ليسمح لتلك المباني أن تبني بأقل من الكود المعتمد
to allow those building to be built to less than code.
وهكذا بدأو ، المواطنين الصحفيين بدأو
And so they started, the citizen journalists started
برصد ذلك كذلك ، وقد كان هناك صورة غير معقولة
reporting that as well. And there was an incredible picture.
قد تكون رأيتموها في الصفححة الأولى لجريدة أوقات نيويورك
You may have seen in on the front page of the New York Times.
مسؤول محلي باطح نفسه حرفيا في الشارع
A local official literally prostrated himself in the street,
أمام هؤلاء المتظاهرين
in front of these protesters,
لكي يبعدهم بعيداً
in order to get them to go away.
أساسا ليقول " أننا سنفعل أي شي لإرضائكم
Essentially to say, "We will do anything to placate you,
فقط توقفوا عن المظاهرات في العلن "
just please stop protesting in public."
ولكن هؤلاء الناس هم من تم إسغلالهم
But these are people who have been radicalized,
لذا شكراً لسياسة الطفل الواحد
because, thanks to the one child policy,
فقد خسروا كل واحد من جيلهم القادم
they have lost everyone in their next generation.
أحد ممن رأي موت طفل واحد
Someone who has seen the death of a single child
الآن ليس لديه شي ليخسره
now has nothing to lose.
لذا فقد استمرت المظاهرات
And so the protest kept going.
وأخيرا فقد أنهار الصينين
And finally the Chinese cracked down.
هذا كان كافي للإعلام المجتمعي
That was enough of citizen media.
حيث بدأو بإعتقال المتظاهرين
And so they began to arrest the protesters.
بدأو بإطفاء القنوات التي يستخدمها المتظاهرين
They began to shut down the media that the protests were happening on.
الصين غالباً هي الاكثر نجاحاً
China is probably the most successful
مدير مراقبة الأنترنت في العالم
manager of Internet censorship in the world,
بإستخدام شي شائع الصيت كسور عزل الصين العظيم
using something that is widely described as the Great Firewall of China.
وسور العزل الأكبر في الصين
And the Great Firewall of China
هو مجموعه من نقاط الملاحظة
is a set of observation points
التي تفترض ان الإعلام منتج من خلال إحترافيين
that assume that media is produced by professionals,
أنها غالباً تأتي من العالم الخارجي
it mostly comes in from the outside world,
انها تأتي في حزم متفرقة نسبياً
it comes in relatively sparse chunks,
وهي تأتي ببطء نسبي كذلك
and it comes in relatively slowly.
وبسبب هذه الصفات الأربع
And because of those four characteristics
فأنه بمقدورهم تصفيتها قبل أن تدخل البلاد
they are able to filter it as it comes into the country.
ولكن مثلما خط ماقينوت
But like the Maginot Line,
الجدار الناري العظيم للصين كان موجهاً للإتجاه الخاطئ
the great firewall of China was facing in the wrong direction
لهذا التحدي
for this challenge,
لأنه أي من الأربع صفات لم تكن صحيحة في هذه البيئة
because not one of those four things was true in this environment.
الإعلام كان يتم إنتاجه محلياً ، كان ينتج من قبل غير الإحترافيين
The media was produced locally. It was produced by amateurs.
وكانت تنتج بسرعه ، وبكميات كبيرة وغير معقولة
It was produced quickly. And it was produced at such an incredible abundance
بذلك لم يكن هناك طريقة لتصفيتها كما تبدوا
that there was no way to filter it as it appeared.
إذا الآن الحكومة الصينية ، والتي لسنين مضت
And so now the Chinese government, who for a dozen years,
تمكنت من فلترة الإنترنت
has quite successfully filtered the web,
هي الآن في موقف القرار
is now in the position of having to decide
هل تسمح أو تطفئ الخدمة بأكملها
whether to allow or shut down entire services,
لأنه بالإنتقال إلى إعلام غير ناضج
because the transformation to amateur media
أنه صعب جدا التعامل معها بطريقه أخرى
is so enormous that they can't deal with it any other way.
وفي الحقيقة أنه حاصل في هذا الأسبوع
And in fact that is happening this week.
في الذكرى العشرين لرجال تينان
On the 20th anniversary of Tiananmen
قد أعلنو منذ يومين مضت
they just, two days ago, announced
أنهم ببساطه سيتم إغلاق خدمة تويتر
that they were simply shutting down access to Twitter,
لأنه لم يكن هناك طريقة لتصفيتها غير ذلك
because there was no way to filter it other than that.
هم يجب أن يغلقو الصنبور بأكمله
They had to turn the spigot entirely off.
الآن هذه التغييرات ، ليس فقط تؤثر على الناس الذين يراقبون الرسائل
Now these changes don't just affect people who want to censor messages.
بل كذلك الذين يودون بعث رسائل
They also affect people who want to send messages,
لأن هذا تحول شامل في النظام البيئي
because this is really a transformation of the ecosystem as a whole,
وليست فقط أستراتيجية محددة
not just a particular strategy.
مشاكل الإعلام التقليدي ، منذ القرن العشرين
The classic media problem, from the 20th century
هو كيف يمكن لمنظمة أن تكون لها رسالة
is, how does an organization have a message
وترغب في نشرها
that they want to get out
لمجموعه من الناس على أطراف الشبكة
to a group of people distributed at the edges of a network.
وهنا هو جواب القرن العشرين
And here is the twentieth century answer.
جمعوا رسائلكم وأرسلوها للكل
Bundle up the message. Send the same message to everybody.
الرسائل الوطنية ، لأشخاص بعينهم
National message. Targeted individuals.
وعدد قليل من المنتجين نسبياً
Relatively sparse number of producers.
غالية جداً
Very expensive to do,
لذا لم يكن هناك الكثير من المنافسة
so there is not a lot of competition.
هكذا أنتم تصلون للناس
This is how you reach people.
كل هذا قد أنتهى
All of that is over.
نحن في أفق يكون فيه الإعلام عالمياً
We are increasingly in a landscape where media is global,
إجتماعي ، وكلي ، ورخيص
social, ubiquitous and cheap.
الآن معظم المنظمات تحاول أن ترسل رسائل
Now most organizations that are trying to send messages
للعالم الخارجي ، لتوزيعها للجمهور المستهدف
to the outside world, to the distributed collection of the audience,
هم الآن يستخدموها لهذا التغيير
are now used to this change.
حيث المتلقي يمكنه الرد على ما طٌرح
The audience can talk back.
وهذا مخيف بعض الشي ، ولكنكم ستعتادون على ذلك بعد فترة ، كما يفعل بقية الناس
And that's a little freaky. But you can get used to it after a while, as people do.
ولكن هذا ليس هو التغيير المجنون الذي نعيش في وسطه
But that's not the really crazy change that we're living in the middle of.
التغيير الحقيقي المجنون هو هنا
The really crazy change is here:
هو في الحقيقة لم تعد غير متصلة ببعضها البعض
it's the fact that they are no longer disconnected from each other,
الحقيقة أن المستهلكين السابقين أصبحو الآن منتجين
the fact that former consumers are now producers,
الحقيقة بأن الجمهور يستطيع كل منهم محادثة الآخر
the fact that the audience can talk directly to one another;
ولأن هناك كثير من عدم النضج مقابل الأحترافية
because there is a lot more amateurs than professionals,
وبسبب حجم الشبكة
and because the size of the network,
وتعقيد الشبكة هو في الحقيقة مربع
the complexity of the network is actually the square
عدد المشاركين
of the number of participants,
بمعنى أن الشبكة عندما تنمو كبيرًا
meaning that the network, when it grows large,
فهي تنمو كبيرا جداً جداً
grows very, very large.
مؤخراً وفي أخر عقد
As recently at last decade,
معظم وسائل الإعلام الموفرة للإستخدام العام
most of the media that was available for public consumption
كانت تنتج من قبل محترفين
was produced by professionals.
هذه الأيام إنتهت
Those days are over, never to return.
إمها الخطوط الخضراء ، التي تعطي محتوى مجاني
It is the green lines now, that are the source of the free content,
والذي يأتي بي لقصة الأخيرة
which brings me to my last story.
لقد رأينا بعض من الإستخدام الخيالي
We saw some of the most imaginative use
في الإعلام الإجتماعي خلال حملة أوباما الإنتخابية
of social media during the Obama campaign.
ولست أعني أن معظم الإستخدام الخيالي هو فقط للسياسة
And I don't mean most imaginative use in politics --
ولكنني أعني أكثر إستخدام خيالي دوماً
I mean most imaginative use ever.
وأحد الأشياء التي فعلها أوباما ، والتي إشتهر بها
And one of the things Obama did, was they famously,
حيث قامت حملة أوباما برفع موقع
the Obama campaign did, was they famously put up
ماي باراك أوباما ، وموقع ماي بي أو
MyBarackObama.com, myBO.com
وملايين المواطنين أحتشدوا ليشاركوا
And millions of citizens rushed in to participate,
ليجربوا ويعرفوا كيف يمكنهم أن يساعدوا
and to try and figure out how to help.
حوارات عظيمة تم طرحها هناك
An incredible conversation sprung up there.
ثم في هذا الوقت من العام الماضي
And then, this time last year,
وقد أعلن أوباما انه سيقوم بتغيير صوته حول فيسا
Obama announced that he was going to change his vote on FISA,
وكالة الإستخبارات والملاحظة الأجنبية
The Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act.
هوقد قال في يناير الماضي ، أنه لن يوقع سنداً
He had said, in January, that he would not sign a bill
قد يسمح لشركات الإتصالات بمراقبة غير مرصودة
that granted telecom immunity for possibly warrantless spying
لأي فرد أمريكي
on American persons.
وفي هذا الصيف ، وفي منتصف حملته العامة
By the summer, in the middle of the general campaign,
هو قال "لقد فكرت في هذا الأمر وقد غيرت رأيي"
He said, "I've thought about the issue more. I've changed my mind.
أنا سأصوت لهذا المطلب
I'm going to vote for this bill."
وكثير من داعميه
And many of his own supporters
وفي موقعه الخاص قد جن جنونهم علناً
on his own site went very publicly berserk.
لقد كان سيناتور أوباما عندما تم إنشائه ، ولكنهم غيروا أسمه لاحقاً
It was Senator Obama when they created it. They changed the name later.
إلى لوسمحت أعطي فيسا حقوقها
"Please get FISA right."
وخلال أيام من إنشاء المجموعه
Within days of this group being created
كانت المجموعه الأكثر نموا في موقع الرئيس
it was the fastest growing group on myBO.com;
وخلال أسابيع من أنشائه أصبحت أكبر مجموعه
within weeks of its being created it was the largest group.
كان على أوباما أن يصدر إعلاناً صحفياً
Obama had to issue a press release.
كان عليه أن يصدر رداً
He had to issue a reply.
وقد قال بوضوح "لقد تفهمت الأمر"
And he said essentially, "I have considered the issue.
وأعرف من أين أنتم تأتون بإعتراضكم
I understand where you are coming from.
ولكنني قدرت كل المعطيات ، وسأصوت كما كنت سأصوت
But having considered it all, I'm still going to vote the way I'm going to vote.
لوكنني أود أن أصلكم وأقول لكم ، أنني أتفهم عدم أتفاقكم معي
But I wanted to reach out to you and say, I understand that you disagree with me,
وبأنني سأتحمل مسؤولية هذا الأمر "
and I'm going to take my lumps on this one."
هذا لم يسعد أحداً ، ولكن لاحقاً شي مضحك حصل في المحادثة
This didn't please anybody. But then a funny thing happened in the conversation.
الناس في المجموعه أكتشفوا
People in that group realized
أن أوباما لم يقفل الخط في وجههم
that Obama had never shut them down.
ولم يحاول أحد في حملة أوباما أن يخفي المجموعه
Nobody in the Obama campaign had ever tried to hide the group
أو أن يجعلها صعبة الإنظمام
or make it harder to join,
أو تجاهل وجودها ، أو مسحها
to deny its existence, to delete it,
أو حذفها من الموقع
to take to off the site.
فقد فهمو أنه دورهم
They had understood that their role
مع موقع الرئيس أنه يساعدوا داعميهم
with myBO.com was to convene their supporters
لا أن يتحكموا فيهم
but not to control their supporters.
وهذا هو النوع من الإنضباطية
And that is the kind of discipline
التي نحتاجها لإستخدام ناضج
that it takes to make really mature use
لهذه الوسيلة الإعلامية
of this media.
الإعلام ، وأفق الإعلام كما عهدناه
Media, the media landscape that we knew,
وكما عرفناه ، ونفس سهولته
as familiar as it was, as easy conceptually as it was
للتعامل مع فكرة أن أحترافيين يبثون
to deal with the idea that professionals broadcast
رسائلهم للغير ناضجين
messages to amateurs,
هو بإزدياد أسلوب قديم
is increasingly slipping away.
في عالم يكون فيه الإعلام عالمي ، وإجتماعي ، وشامل ، ورخيص
In a world where media is global, social, ubiquitous and cheap,
في عالم يكون فيه المستمعن القدامى
in a world of media where the former audience
هم بزيادة يصبحون مشاركين
are now increasingly full participants,
في هذا العالم ، الإعلام أقل وأقل
in that world, media is less and less often
يحاول توصيل رسالة واحدة
about crafting a single message
لتستهلك من الأفراد
to be consumed by individuals.
أنه أكثر وأكثر إحتمالية
It is more and more often
لتكون طريقة لخلق بيئية مناسبة
a way of creating an environment for convening
ودعم المجموعات
and supporting groups.
والأختيار الذي نواجهه
And the choice we face,
أعني كل من لديه رسالة يودون أن تسمع
I mean anybody who has a message they want to have heard
في أي مكان بالعالم
anywhere in the world,
هل هي البيئة الإعلامية التي نود نعمل خلالها
isn't whether or not that is the media environment we want to operate in.
هذه البيئة الإعلامية التي لدينا
That's the media environment we've got.
و السؤال الذي يجب أن نواجهه الآن
The question we all face now is,
" كيف يمكننا فعلاً الإستخدام الأفضل لهذا الإعلام ؟
"How can we make best use of this media?
حتى لوكان يعني تغيير الطريقة التي كنا دائما نفعلها بها
Even though it means changing the way we've always done it."
شكرا جزيلاً لكم
Thank you very much.
(تصفيق)